<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>

   <ENTRY context="proposaltools" key="pimms" refkeywords="pimms prop_pimms simulator" seealsogroups="prop-tools">

   <SYNOPSIS>
    PIMMS (Portable, Interactive Multi-Mission Simulator)
    converts source fluxes and count rates between missions.  
   </SYNOPSIS>

<ADDRESS><URL>pimms.html</URL></ADDRESS>
<ADDRESS><URL>http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/pimms.html</URL></ADDRESS>
    


   <DESC>
      <PARA>
	PIMMS can be run over the web using a browser or run locally
	using the command-line interface (CLI). Note that as of
	Chandra Cycle 13 (December 2010), PIMMS is not part of the CIAO Proposal
	toolkit and users wishing to use the CLI version need to
	download PIMMS from HEASARC at 
	<HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/software/tools/pimms.html">http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/software/tools/pimms.html</HREF>.
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	PIMMS is a tool for estimating the source flux or count rate
	for a specific mission from either a count rate estimated by a
	previous mission or flux in some energy bound. It is very
	useful for simple source spectra, but not for complicated
	spectral or spatial structures. PIMMS also estimates the
	amount of Chandra ACIS pile-up assuming a point source
	on-axis, and accounts for this when estimating count
	rates. The tool was developed at NASA-GSFC, and the CXC
	implemented its own version for use as a Chandra proposal
	planning tool. Detailed information concerning PIMMS is available at:
        <HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/software/tools/pimms.html">http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/software/tools/pimms.html</HREF>.
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Latest Effective Areas">
	The latest Chandra effective area
	curves are always included in the CXC web version of PIMMS as
	well as in the CLI version downloadable from HEASARC. The CXC
	web version of PIMMS also includes Chandra  effective area
	curves for past proposing cycles going back to cycle 3. Users
	wishing to install older versions of Chandra effective area
	curves on top of the HEASARC CLI version of PIMMS should
	contact the Chandra Helpdesk. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="ACIS Pile-up">
        As mentioned above, PIMMS estimates the effect of pile-up on
	ACIS counting rates. However, if a grating is inserted, the
	impacts of pile up are only estimated for the counting rate of 
	the zeroth order image.The pile-up fraction in PIMMS software
	is defined as the ratio of the number of frames with two or
	more spurious pile-up events to the number of frames with a
	single, unpiled event. Note that the command-line version of
	PIMMS assumes that the entire ACIS bandpass is used. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Raymond-Smith Models">		
	(1) The calculation only extends to 8 keV regardless of output
	AND input energy ranges. Any input model will be truncated at
	8 keV, no attempt will be made to "convert" counts above 8  
	keV. Similarly, the output gives flux/counts up to 8 keV. (2)
	The available temperatures are listed in a pop-up menu from
	which the user selects that closest to the desired
	temperature. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Running PIMMS Over the Web">
	 PIMMS can be accessed via the URL:
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/toolkit/pimms.jsp">http://cxc.harvard.edu/toolkit/pimms.jsp</HREF>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	A general help file for the Proposal Planning Toolkit is
	available by clicking the 'HELP' button.  Descriptions for
	each parameter may be found by clicking the appropriate
	parameter name. The web version of PIMMS has some features not
	found in the command-line version, such as background count
	rates for Chandra mission, the ACIS frame time option, and the
	truncation of energy at 8 keV in Raymond-Smith Models. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="Background Count Rates">
        The web version of PIMMS provides background in a 1.5" radius 
	circle for imaging (ACIS or HRC) observations. Extended source
	size specification affects only background determination.
	PIMMS also estimates the background per resolution element for
	HRC-S/LETG spectra. 
      </PARA>

      <PARA title="ACIS Frame Time">
	In the web version of PIMMS, the user can either enter the
	ACIS frame time or choose to have PIMMS calculate the most
	efficient frame time for a given number of CCDs and
	sub-array. In the latter case, PIMMS will calculate the frame
	time that results in the least amount of pile-up and will
	present the corresponding results. The actual frame time used
	in performing these calculations can be examined using the
	"View Output" button.  
      </PARA>


      <PARA title="Running PIMMS from the Command Line">
	The command-line version of PIMMS can be downloaded from 
	<HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/software/tools/pimms.html">http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/software/tools/pimms.html</HREF>
      </PARA>

      <PARA>
	The HEASARC web site also
	includes <HREF link="http://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/software/tools/pimms.html#user">a PIMMS user guide</HREF>, and there is a 'HELP' command in
	PIMMS. Contact the CXC Helpdesk for any problems related to
	running the CLI version of PIMMS with Chandra data. 
     </PARA>

     </DESC>

<VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
<LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>