<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "CXCHelp.dtd">
<cxchelptopics>
<ENTRY context="proposaltools" key="prop-tools" refkeywords="proposal proposing tools" seealsogroups="prop-tools">
<SYNOPSIS>

Tools that aid in the preparation and submission of Chandra proposals

</SYNOPSIS>
<ADDRESS>
<URL>
prop-tools.html
</URL>

</ADDRESS>
<ADDRESS>
<URL>
http://cxc.harvard.edu/ciao/ahelp/prop-tools.html
</URL>

</ADDRESS>
<DESC>
<PARA>

Below we list tools available to help in feasibility studies,
proposal preparation, and proposal submission.   Refer to the <HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/proposer/">
Proposer area </HREF> of the Chandra X-ray Center web site for links to these tools and the most current proposing information.  

</PARA>
<PARA title="Tools that Access the Chandra Observation Catalog Database">
 
  To obtain information about observations that have already taken
place or have been approved to take place with Chandra, use 
Web ChaSeR to search the Chandra Data Archive.  See the 
<HREF link="http://cxc.harvard.edu/cda/">Chandra Archive web pages</HREF>
 for more information.
</PARA>

<PARA title="Tools for Assessing Feasibility">

The following tools will aid in determining the feasibility of using
one of the Chandra detectors to observe a specific target.  When
appropriately used, they can help provide a reasonable estimate of
exposure time.
</PARA>
<LIST>
<ITEM>
PIMMS (Portable Interactive Multi-Mission Simulator) -- use
when there is an estimate of source flux for a simple source spectra
from either a count rate estimated from a previous mission or a flux
in some energy band; estimates the amount of ACIS pile-up on the count
rate
</ITEM>
<ITEM>
Sherpa or XSPEC -- to provide a simulation of more complicated spectra
 estimates spectral shape and uncertainty; some pile-up modeling capability
</ITEM>
<ITEM>
MARX (Model of AXAF's Response to X-rays) -- for a source with
complicated spatial structure; perform Monte-Carlo simulation of the
observation, including approximation to mirror and instrument
characteristics; output is a simulated data set that can be analyzed
with CIAO and other data analysis packages; simulates ACIS pile-up
</ITEM>

</LIST>
<PARA title="Proposal Planning Tools">

These tools aid in the preparation of a Chandra proposal, in particular: 
evaluating target visibility and observing constraints, and converting between 
date/time systems and coordinate systems. These are available either
over the web, or through a command-line interface; refer to ahelp
files for the individual tools for more information. 
</PARA>
<LIST>
<ITEM>
COLDEN -- calculate galactic neutral hydrogen column
density
</ITEM>
<ITEM>
DATES --  perform interactive calendar and time conversions
</ITEM>
<ITEM>
PRECESS --  perform astronomical coordinate conversions
</ITEM>
<ITEM>
ObsVis -- (command-line interface only) allows inspection of instrument fields-of-view,
observatory roll angle and target visibility
</ITEM>
<ITEM>
PRoVis -- (web only) interactively plots Chandra spacecraft pitch, roll and visibility by date for any celestial target
</ITEM>
</LIST>
<PARA title="Chandra Proposal Submission">

Electronic submission of proposal information is required. The
scientific justification must also be submitted electronically.  Paper
copies will be accepted only from individuals without access to the
Internet.  

</PARA>
<LIST>
<ITEM>
WWW version of the Remote Proposal Submission (RPS) system -- a
form-based interface to proposal processor; links exist to help for
each page of the form and for each parameter;  generic RPS help is
available at the top of the form. The form is available through the
Proposer page URL at the top of this file.

</ITEM>
<ITEM>
E-mail server of the RPS system -- instructions for use may be
obtained by sending a blank e-mail message to
rps@head.cfa.harvard.edu; note that if you are unable to send a
message with no subject or text, enter a single character in either
position; the response will be an ASCII file of instructions.
</ITEM>

</LIST>

</DESC>
<VERSION>CIAO 4.5</VERSION>
<LASTMODIFIED>December 2012</LASTMODIFIED>

</ENTRY>

</cxchelptopics>
