<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE cxchelptopics SYSTEM "/data/udoc2/xml/CXCHelp.dtd"    []>
   <cxchelptopics>
   <ENTRY key="RPS" context="proposaltools" refkeywords="proposal submission"
seealsogroups="colden dates pimms precess">
   <SYNOPSIS>
 Remote Proposal Submission (RPS) is for the electronic submission of
Chandra proposals.  This includes observation requests for the NRA
cycle, requests to observe a TOO already approved during an NRA,  new
out-of_cycle TOOs, Director's Discretionary Time, and Chandra cost proposals.
   </SYNOPSIS>
   
<DESC>
<PARA>
RPS is available in two forms;  there is a WWW version (requiring a
browser that supports frames), and there is an email server.  The WWW
version is accessed through the Proposers section of the CXC web
page (http://cxc.harvard.edu/proposer). Instructions for using the
email server can be received by sending an email message to
rps@head.cfa.harvard.edu with the following lines in the message:
</PARA>  
<VERBATIM>
  &lt;BEGIN&gt;
  &lt;OPTION=HELP&gt;
  &lt;END&gt;
</VERBATIM>

<PARA title="WWW Version of RPS"> </PARA>
<PARA>
Please note that RPS is stateless, so any work must be saved by the
user. Nothing is done with input until one of the action buttons is
pushed. Be certain to save your form entries often. You can save the 
html file to your local disk using the RPS Save button and then
reload it either using the browser 'File->Open' capability or the
'Reload' button on the RPS form for older browsers.
</PARA>
<PARA>
The WWW version consists of the Cover Page, General Form, and Target
Form.  The blue triangles (left side of first RPS page) toggle between a
collapsed page (the initial appearance) and an expanded page. If you
have several targets, RPS will work faster if you keep only one target
at a time expanded. Depending on the speed of your internet connection,
you may want to consider using the e-mail version if you have several 
targets.
</PARA>
<PARA> There are also several action buttons at the top of the page, these
are:</PARA>
<PARA>	Add Target - Target adding and Cloning Form </PARA>
 <PARA>     Delete Target - remove a target form - must have set
'delete target' flag at top of the form of the target to be deleted
(note the target numbers will appear to be wrong after a target is
deleted: the processor WILL correct this when the LaTeX form is
generated) </PARA> 
<PARA>        Feedback - opens a sub-window for sending comments,
complaints, etc. to Chandra X-Ray Center.</PARA>  
<PARA>        LaTeX - obtain the LaTeX version; save after receipt
(blank forms may be obtained by using the LaTeX button BEFORE entering
any information into the form)</PARA>  
<PARA>        PDF - obtain the PDF version; save after receipt </PARA>
<PARA>        Re-load - Reload previously saved HTML form (only available for 
older browsers)</PARA>
<PARA>        Save - save the values entered in the form boxes as HTML </PARA>
<PARA>        Submit - submit the electronic version to the proposal
database - this should be used as the next-to-LAST step. The submit
button  will not appear on the form until after the proposal has been 'verified' successfully.</PARA> 
<PARA>        Upload Science Justification- submit the science justification 
(PDF file). The user should *not* upload the justification until the forms
have been  submitted. A proposal number is returned with the
acknowledgment of receipt of the forms. That proposal number is used
to put the justification and the forms into one PDF file for printing at CXC. </PARA>
<PARA>        Verify - send the electronic version for verification 
</PARA>
<PARA>
After all proposal data are entered into the three form sections, the
data need to be verified for completeness and accuracy.  Use the
VERIFY button on the RPS form.  Save the verified proposal to a local
disk, using the SAVE button. Use the LaTeX button to generate a LaTeX
file.  
</PARA>
<PARA>
Once the form is saved and a PDF science justification has been
created, use the SUBMIT button to submit the proposal to the CXC.
This should be done only once per proposal.  Then UPLOAD SCIENCE JUSTIFICATION 
PDF version by providing the full path name to the file when requested by RPS.
</PARA>
<PARA>There are links to help for each parameter in the form.  Generic help
is also available at the top of the page.  Note there are different
versions of RPS for Cost proposals, DDT and TOOs, these are also available
through the Proposer section of the CXC web pages.</PARA>




</DESC>


<VERSION>
Chandra RPS(Cycle 9) 
</VERSION>
<LASTMODIFIED>
October 2006
</LASTMODIFIED>
</ENTRY>
</cxchelptopics>
   
